It is a very long way.
And there is a lot of work.
It is.
Namely
the books or book like this one, the "river"
and the “overstinner and“ coupe No. 6 ”
They demand
Many years of work.
When I started,
It was so that I wished I
would become a teacher in Russian.
And many stories
If people who have lived there once,
in history,
in that rural village and what had happened during
that time.
I have grown up with an oral storytelling tradition.
It is the same as reading books and
The storytelling tradition was so strong,
I have listened to,
All year round, on different stories.
In my hometown was there,
Although it is like the same language.
When I start writing on meänkieli
so it came like fluent
from my body.
For that is what I have
grown up with.
I was 15 years old when I moved from that countryside
Because
I wanted to study
It was 70s
and the first idea
Laestadians live there.
Rovaniemi was Storbyn
But it was the 70s and one did
at that time
Vodka travel.
Vodka - slug, glow, glow
Travel to Russia
And the trips went to Murmansk
For that murmansk was the largest
the nearest big village
To Rovaniemi.
did i go to the bus
and traveled to Murmansk.
Murmansk is there
on the bank of the ice sea
And when I saw the town
Was I so surprised
because
At that time it lived
Half a million people there.
There all kinds of
Restaurants.
But one could not
Shipping cows with rowing boat.
So one had to build such
Terrible ferries.
The Torne River is large
The water rushes very fast
so it is very dangerous to cross the river
with such a ferry and with many cows
fell off and drowned.
Nearly 30,000 cows
was brought to Sweden.
The camps in Sweden and so on, that there were so many as evacuated.
What do you think it is?
When I was a kid and teenager
I heard these stories by my relatives.
But it was not popular to talk about that time
Because people felt shame.
They felt shame that they were refugees
It is perfectly normal for people to feel that way.
These are such psychological reactions.
They did not want to talk about it that we have been refugees or
that conditions in the camps were very hard.
People wanted to forget about it
And just start building a new life.
But no books about
This situation in Lapland
It's true
Then this book is, after all,
I would almost say unfortunately, uncomfortably relevant considering the situation we have today.
There are still corresponding phenomena.
To write this book, you must at least take part in research.
Was there a lot of work around?
I am so pleased that
Researchers and historians
has made
lots of
forced to become an adult because of the circumstances.
And then she is also a reflective person, she ponders about
the universe.
She ponders nature, she ponders the starry sky.
And so she is very responsible
Pretty incredible indeed!
What strikes me among other things is that
We have Christianity, we have science
and all that
Is included in her consciousness as she thinks about the world.
And another thing
which is also so fascinating, this is the relationship with nature,
The nature that surrounds her and all the others and how you write this nature it is incredibly beautiful.
You look like exactly,
It is noticeable that you are a painter
For as you reproduce nature through this girl
and relationship with the animals
For that is also all
specifically.
After all, it becomes a value scale, what is it that matters and what does nothing mean?
If I am going to pick something out of this then I thought
It is very important,
Everything she says is very important in this book.
If I think about relationships with nature ...
First I can tell you a little about that girl.
When I wrote the book and looked at the world
with that girl's eyes that is 13-14 years old,
Which is very eager, who want to know about life.
She wants to know about everything that happens everything that has happened.
She is full of
eenergy and she is full of the joy of life
Although she is in liver in such strange
situations.
How to live
together with animals.
She thinks she is part of nature
Like the trees,
Like the earth, as well as the air,
Like all flowers.
So she
does not have a relationship
to nature,
She is part of nature.
Like we are actually.
and grandmother's engagement gifts,
A coffee pot of silver, cream and sugar bowl.
He had smile pits and his hand felt good.
We walked along Skogsvägen to the lake.
The water chuckled and sparkled.
The swallows piled here and there, very close to the surface,
caught short and long night dragonflies in the beak and swung back up into the blue sky
I jerked when the bay put my hand on my shoulder,
hugged hard about it,
Folded me on my back and rolled over on me.
A shoal small fish swam around in my stomach and constantly changed the direction.
The lungs are on fire, the heart fluttered like a summer curtain in an open window.
I thought now is the right time and pressed lips against his rough lips,
Did he licked sweaty face,
he tickled smile pits and white teeth with my tongue.
He my cheeks.
My stupid arms felt the curled hair on his arms.
I brought my pants down and opened the buttons in his.
He penetrated into my damp pussy and it splashed and irritated in my toes and fingertips.
Life sprinkled in the mouth.
I screamed like a pig.
It felt like the lungs were emptied of air and I fell hover like the leaf from the tree.
He sprayed the liquids into my interior.
I grabbed his head and pushed it down in my wrote and he started licking.
My leather pounded satisfied.
We lay next to each other, we giggled and let lice flies and mosquito suck blood out of the throat and forest locks run over our faces.
Then we were silent.
I looked at his mouth, forehead and clear eyes.
We were lying side by side,
close together,
breasts against breasts,
without words.
And the feeling of joy pulsed all the way into the nails.
The original is at Meänkieli and the assignment was to translate it into Swedish, not into another dialect.
I can't translate to another dialect because I know no dialect so good that I can write it on it.
Then i have thought like that
that I try to catch the rhythm
In the original as good as possible.
Of course you should include the message too, but it should float in your own rhythm.
Yes simply so ...
Any of you may have read the translations of
Väinö Linnas "Unknown Soldier"
to Swedish?
And that is, as always, this question with dialect?
What to do with the dialect?
So I hear in my head that here he was told me in Swedish.
I don't know how it goes but ...
She knows me so well!
We have known each other for 20 years
"The Supreme" is also on Meänkieli
Coupbee No. 6 is in original in Finnish
These are short stories that are also translated into Swedish.
Such short stories that I wrote before I started writing novels.
I was 50 years old when I started,
not 50 years,
I was 40 years old when I started writing novels.
Nowadays, short stories.
Most to actors.
Monologists
to actors.
If you have written about your life in Russia and in Denmark and in the US
Yes, I have written about my life in Russia, Kupé # 6 which is the novel and also the movie.
So it is from my own life that and my first
Trans -Siberian journey that I did
null
First year with gorbatov
Now I work with the book about Texas
With film
In different countries
So i saw it four times and each
It was like another movie to me
For the first time it was like all that since I started
Focus on dialogues then on clothes and
Darke like that so
And then the music and all these sounds and
Looks the lice and such so it was always a new movie
No but that yes recommended
And the book is like its
My mother came as a four -year -old
And she is not written language.
She is spoken language.
In Swedish only.
So that may be a reason.
But I would like ...
I hear when you tell us about coupe # 6
That you might not have the power over the movie
I would like to ask you
Whether you live or not when the movie of the river
Made in the future, that you retain power and say they may not find a name for this girl.
In order to,
For example, Margaret Atwood has made a book
where the main character had no name and
The film companies have demanded that she get a name and they have said that she is called something.
Keep in mind that there is a risk that they suddenly
Just decide that she is called Seja or what she can now be called.
I keep it in my heart
But I was still thinking about coupe No. 6
For
The girl there
Have only one replica in the whole novel, the rest is going on in her head.
We get to know it through her thoughts, it's related ...
interesting.
So that is the reason for that
I write long monologues.
You have a very fun explanation for why monologue?
And that is, I have thought about why I love to write monologues
It is that in Finland and especially in my hometown
we usually do not discuss.
There are no dialogues.
There are only
Monologist by monologue.
You do not discuss.
It's another culture
than in Sweden.
We know that